<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: module | Nice R Code]]></title>
  <link href="http://nicercode.github.io/blog/categories/module/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://nicercode.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-16T12:05:39+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://nicercode.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rich FitzJohn & Daniel Falster]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Organizing the project directory]]></title>
    <link href="http://nicercode.github.io/blog/2013-05-17-organising-my-project/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-17T08:20:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nicercode.github.io/blog/organising-my-project</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a guest post by Marcela Diaz, a PhD student at Macquarie University. </p>

<p>Until recently, I hadn’t given much attention to organising files in my project. All the documents and files from my current project were spread out in two different folders, with very little sub folder division. All the files where together in the same place and I had multiple versions of the same file, with different dates. As you can see, things were getting a bit out of control.</p>

<!--more -->
<p><img src="../../images/2013-05-17-organising-my-project/directory1_before.png"></p>

<p><img src="../../images/2013-05-17-organising-my-project/directory2_before.png"></p>

<p>Following <a href="../2013-04-05-projects/">advice from by Rich and Daniel</a>, I decided to spend a little time getting organised, adopting a directory layout with the following folders:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Data: which contains both my base (raw) data and the processed data </li>
  <li>Output: data and figures generated in R</li>
  <li>R: R scripts with all new functions I created as part of the cleaning directory process and in an attempt to write nicer code. </li>
  <li>Analysis (R file): R script sourcing all the functions necessary for the analysis </li>
</ul>

<p><img src="../../images/2013-05-17-organising-my-project/directory_after.png"></p>

<p>At the same time I <a href="../../git">started using version control with git</a>. As a result, I no longer need to create a new file every time I make a change, and each of the files in the analysis directory is unique.</p>

<p>Setting up the new directory and sorting the existing files in the new folders didn’t take long and was relatively easy. Now it is really simple to find files and keep track of current and old figures. I no longer need to use spotlight to find the latest version of each script. From my experience this improved the organization and efficiency of my project; I  highly recommend keeping a good project layout. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[git]]></title>
    <link href="http://nicercode.github.io/blog/2013-04-23-git/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-23T17:51:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://nicercode.github.io/blog/git</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to everyone who came along and was such good sports with
learning git today. Hopefully you now have enough tools to help you use git in your own
projects. The notes are available (in fairly raw form)
<a href="/git">here</a>. Please let us know where they are unclear and we will
update them.</p>

<p>To re-emphasise our closing message – start using it on a
project, start thinking about what you want to track, and start
thinking about what constitutes a logical commit.  Once you get into a
rhythm it will seem much easier.  Bring your questions along to the
class in 2 weeks time.</p>

<p>Also, to re-emphasise that git is not a backup system.  Make sure that
you have your work backed up, just in case something terrible happens.
I recommend <a href="http://www.crashplan.com/">crash plan</a> which you can use
for free for backing up onto external hard drives (and for a fee).</p>

<h2 id="feedback">Feedback</h2>

<p>We welcome any and all feedback on the material and how we present it.
You can give <em>anonymous</em> feedback by emailing G2G admin (you should
have the address already – I’m only not putting it up here in a vain
effort to slow down spam bots).  Alternatively, you are welcome to
email either or both of us, or leave a comment on a relevant page.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why I want to write nice R code]]></title>
    <link href="http://nicercode.github.io/blog/2013-04-05-why-nice-code/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-05T14:46:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nicercode.github.io/blog/why-nice-code</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<!--
Why are students here
Goals: performance, learning, affective, social
Value: attainment, intrinsic, instrumental

Instrumental - allows you to accomplish other important goals (extrinsic
rewards), i.e. learn about world, write papers, impress others
Intrinsic - value nice code for itself (craftsmanship)
Attainment -  satisfaction in getting something to work
-->

<p>Writing code is fast becoming a key - if not the most important - skill for
doing research in the 21st century. As scientists, we live in extraordinary
times. The amount of data (information) available to us is increasing
exponentially, allowing for rapid advances in our understanding of the world
around us. The amount of information contained in a standard scientific paper
also seems to be on the rise. Researchers therefore need to be able to handle
ever larger amounts of data to ask novel questions and get papers published.
Yet, the standard tools used by many biologists -  point and click programs for
manipulating data, doing stats and making plots - do not allow us to scale-up
our analyses to match data availability, at least not without many, many more
‘clicks’.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p><span class='caption-wrapper right'><img class='caption' src='/images/2013-04-05-why-nice-code/geeks-vs-nongeeks-repetitive-tasks.png' width='' height='' alt='Why writing code saves you time with repetitive tasks, by <a href="https://plus.google.com/+BrunoOliveira/posts/MGxauXypb1Y">Bruno Oliveira</a>' title='Why writing code saves you time with repetitive tasks, by <a href="https://plus.google.com/+BrunoOliveira/posts/MGxauXypb1Y">Bruno Oliveira</a>'><span class='caption-text'>Why writing code saves you time with repetitive tasks, by <a href="https://plus.google.com/+BrunoOliveira/posts/MGxauXypb1Y">Bruno Oliveira</a></span></span></p>

<p>The solution is to write scripts in programs like
<a href="http://www.r-project.org/">R</a>, <a href="http://www.python.org/">python</a> or
<a href="http://www.mathworks.com.au/products/matlab/">matlab</a>. Scripting allows you to
automate analyses, and therefore scale-up without a big increase in
effort.</p>

<p>Writing code also offers other benefits to research. When your
analyses are documented in a script, it is easier to pick up a project and
start working on it again. You have a record of what you did and why. Chunks
of code can also be reused in new projects, saving vast amount of time. Writing
code also allows for effective collaboration with people from all over the
world. For all these reasons, many researchers are now learning how to write
code.</p>

<p>Yet, most researchers have no or limited formal training in computer science,
and thus struggle to write nice code (<a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/467775a">Merali 2010</a>). Most of us are self-taught, having used a
mix of books, advice from other amateur coders, internet posts, and lots of
trial and error. Soon after have we written our first R script, our hard drives
explode with large bodies of barely readable code that we only half understand,
that also happens to be full of bugs and is generally difficult to use. Not
surprisingly, many researchers find writing code to be a relatively painful
process, involving lots of trial and error and, inevitably, frustration.</p>

<p>If this sounds familiar to you, don’t worry, you are not alone. There are many
<a href="/intro/resources.html">great R resources</a> available, but most show you how
to do some fancy trick, e.g. run some complicated statistical test or make a
fancy plot. Few people - outside of computer science departments - spend time
discussing the qualities of nice code and teaching you good coding habits.
Certainly no one is teaching you these skills in your standard biology research
department.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Learn to code! I worry that most biologists leave uni lacking #1 skill for 21st cent biology. For inspiration <a href="http://t.co/7lzRutYuIw" title="http://code.org">code.org</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23CODE">#CODE</a></p>&mdash; Daniel Falster (@adaptive_plant) <a href="https://twitter.com/adaptive_plant/status/306854385076543488">February 27, 2013</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="http://nicercode.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<p>Observing how colleagues were struggling with their code, we
(<a href="/about#Team">Rich FitzJohn and Daniel Falster</a>) have teamed up to bring you
the <a href="http://nicercode.github.io/">nice R code</a> course and blog. We are
targeting researchers who are already using R and want to take their coding to
the next level. Our goal is to help you write nicer code.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>By ‘nicer’ we mean
code that is easy to read, easy to write, runs fast, gives reliable results, is
easy to reuse in new projects, and is easy to share with collaborators.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We
will be focussing on elements of workflow, good coding habits and some tricks,
that will help transform your code from messy to nice.</p>

<p>The inspiration for nice R code came in part from attending a boot camp run by
Greg Wilson from the <a href="http://software-carpentry.org/">software carpentry team</a>.
These boot camps aim to help researchers be more productive by teaching them
basic computing skills. Unlike other software courses we had attended, the
focus in the boot camps was on good programming habits and design. As
biologists, we saw a need for more material focussed on R, the language that
has come to dominate biological research. We are not experts, but have more
experience than many biologists. Hence the nice R code blog.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>@<a href="https://twitter.com/phylorich">phylorich</a> Being able to code (in any language) is most important skill for current biology. R is good choice: widely used, high level, free</p>&mdash; Daniel Falster (@adaptive_plant) <a href="https://twitter.com/adaptive_plant/status/312438921059520512">March 15, 2013</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="http://nicercode.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<h2 id="key-elements-of-nice-r-code">Key elements of nice R code</h2>
<p>We will now briefly consider some of the key principles of writing nice code.</p>

<h3 id="nice-code-is-easy-to-read">Nice code is easy to read</h3>

<p><blockquote><p>Programs should be written for people to read, and only incidentally for<br/>machines to execute.</p><footer><strong>Abelson and Sussman</strong> <cite>Structure and Interpretation of Computer Programs</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Readability is by far the most important guiding principle for writing nicer
code. <strong>Anyone (especially you) should be able to pick up any of your
projects, understand what the code does and how to run it</strong>. Most code
written for research purposes is not easy to read.</p>

<p>In our opinion, there are no fixed rules for what nice code should look like.
There
is just a single test: is it easy to read? To check how nice your code
is, pass it to a collaborator, or pick up some code you haven’t used for
over a year. Do they (you) understand it?</p>

<p>Below are some general guidelines for making your code more readable. We
will explore each of these in more detail here on the blog:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Use a sensible directory structure for organising project related
materials.</li>
  <li>Abstract your code into many small functions with helpful descriptive
names</li>
  <li>Use comments, design features, and meaningful variable or function names
to capture the intent of your code, i.e. describe what it is <em>meant</em> to do</li>
  <li>Use version control. Of the many reasons for using version control, one is
that it archives older versions of your code, permitting you to ruthlessly
yet safely delete old files. This helps reduce clutter and improves readability.</li>
  <li>Apply a consistent style, such as that described in  the</li>
  <li><a href="http://google-styleguide.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/google-r-style.html">google R style guide</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="nice-code-is-reliable-ie-bug-free">Nice code is reliable, i.e. bug free</h3>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>Occma's raz0r: if your program isn't working, it's probably just a typo in the code, not an undiscovered bug or thing you're doing wrong</p>&mdash; Alison Abreu-Garcia (@alisonag) <a href="https://twitter.com/alisonag/status/322374461212995584">April 11, 2013</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="http://nicercode.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<p>The computer does exactly what you tell it to. If there is a problem in your code, it’s most likely you put it there. How certain
are you that your code is error free? More than once I have reached a state
of near panic, looking over my code to ensure it is bug free before
submitting a final version of a paper for publication. What if I got it wrong?</p>

<p><a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1109/MCSE.2005.54">It is almost impossible to ensure code is bug free</a>, but one can adopt healthy
habits that minimise the chance of this occurring:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Don’t repeat yourself. The less you type, the fewer chances there are for
mistakes</li>
  <li>Use test scripts, to compare your code against known cases</li>
  <li>Avoid using global variables, the attach function and <a href="../intro/bad-habits.html">other nasties</a>
where ownership of data cannot be ensured</li>
  <li>Use version control so that you see what has changed, and easily trace
mistakes</li>
  <li>Wherever possible, open your code and project up for review, either by
colleagues, during review process, or in repositories such as github.</li>
  <li>The more <em>readable</em> your code is, the less likely it is to contain
errors.</li>
</ul>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>"Every bug is two bugs: the bug in your code, and the test you didn't write"@<a href="https://twitter.com/estherbester">estherbester</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/search/%23pycon">#pycon</a></p>&mdash; Ned Batchelder (@nedbat) <a href="https://twitter.com/nedbat/status/312628852558032896">March 15, 2013</a></blockquote>
<script async="" src="http://nicercode.github.io//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>

<h3 id="nice-code-runs-quickly-and-is-therefore-a-pleasure-to-use">Nice code runs quickly and is therefore a pleasure to use</h3>

<blockquote>
  <p>The faster you can make the plot, the more fun you will have.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Code that is slow to run is less fun to use. By <em>slow</em> I mean anything
that takes more than a few seconds to run, so impedes analysis.
Speed is particularly an issue for people analysing large datasets, or
running complex simulations, where code may run for many hours, days,
or weeks.</p>

<p>Some effective strategies for making code run faster:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Abstract your code into functions, so that you can compare different
versions</li>
  <li>Use code profiling to identify the main computational bottlenecks
and improve them</li>
  <li>Think carefully about algorithm design</li>
  <li>Understand why some operations are intrinsically slower
than others, e.g. why a <code>for</code> loop is slower than using <code>lapply</code></li>
  <li>Use multiple processors to increase computing power, either in your
own machine or by running your code on a cluster.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="the-benefits-of-writing-nicer-code">The benefits of writing nicer code</h2>
<p>There are many benefits of writing nicer code:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Better science</strong>: nice code allows you to handle bigger data sets and has less bugs.</li>
  <li><strong>More fun</strong>: spend less time wrestling with R, and more time working with data.</li>
  <li><strong>Become more efficient</strong>: Nice code is reusable, sharable, and quicker to run.</li>
  <li><strong>Future employment</strong>: You should consider anything you write (open or closed) to be a potential advert to a future employer. Code has impact. Code sharing <a href="http://resume.github.io/?cboettig">sites like github now make resumes for you</a>, to capture your impact.  Scientists with an analytical bent are often <a href="http://www.nature.com/naturejobs/science/articles/10.1038/nj7440-271">sought-after in the natural sciences</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>If you need further motivation, consider this advice</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper centre'><img class='caption' src='/images/2013-04-05-why-nice-code/Maniac.jpg' width='' height='' alt='An <a href="http://www.winsoft.se/2009/08/the-maintainer-might-be-a-maniac-serial-killer">advisory pop-up for MS Visual C++</a>' title='An <a href="http://www.winsoft.se/2009/08/the-maintainer-might-be-a-maniac-serial-killer">advisory pop-up for MS Visual C++</a>'><span class='caption-text'>An <a href="http://www.winsoft.se/2009/08/the-maintainer-might-be-a-maniac-serial-killer">advisory pop-up for MS Visual C++</a></span></span></p>

<p>This might seem extreme, until you realise that the maniac serial killer is
<strong>you</strong>, and you definitely know where you live.</p>

<p>At some point, you will
return to nearly every piece of code you wrote and need to understand it
afresh. If it is messy code, you will spend a lot of time going over it to
understand what you did, possibly a week, month, year or decade ago. Although
you are unlikely get so frustrated as to seek bloody revenge on your former
self, you might come close.
<blockquote><p>The single biggest reason you should write nice code is so that your future<br/> self can understand it.</p><footer><strong>Greg Wilson</strong> <cite>Software Carpentry Course</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>As a by product, code that is easy to read is also easy to
reuse in new projects and share with colleagues, including as online
supplementary material. Increasingly, journals are requiring code be submitted
as part of the review process and these are often published online. Alas, much of the
current crop of code is difficult to read. At best, having messy code may reduce
the impact of your paper. But you might also get rejected because the
reviewer couldn’t understand your code. At worst, some people have had to <a href="http://www.sciencemag.org/content/314/5807/1856.summary">retract high profile work because of bugs in their code</a>.</p>

<p>It’s time to write some nice R code.</p>

<p>For further inspiration, you may like to check out Greg Wilson’s great article “<a href="http://arxiv.org/abs/1210.0530">Best Practices for Scientific Computing</a>.”</p>

<p><strong>Acknowledgments:</strong> Many thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/gvwilson">Greg Wilson</a>, <a href="http://inundata.org/">Karthik Ram</a>, <a href="http://schamberlain.github.io/scott/">Scott Chameberlain</a> and <a href="http://www.carlboettiger.info/">Carl Boettiger</a> and <a href="http://www.zoology.ubc.ca/~fitzjohn/">Rich FitzJohn</a> for inspirational chats, code and work.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Plans for 'Nice R code module', Macquarie University 2013]]></title>
    <link href="http://nicercode.github.io/blog/2013-03-08-nice-r-code-2013-plans/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-08T09:58:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nicercode.github.io/blog/nice-r-code-2013-plans</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to the Nice R code module. This module is targeted at researchers who 
are already using R and want to write nicer code. By ‘nicer’ we mean code that 
is easy to write, is easy to read, runs fast, gives reliable results, is easy 
to reuse in new projects, and is easy to share with collaborators. When you 
write nice code, you do better science, are more productive, and have more fun.</p>

<p>We have a tentative schedule of plans for the 2013 Nice R Code module. The 
module consists of 9 one hour sessions and one 3 hour session. 
The topics covered fall into two broad categories: <em>workflow</em> and
<em>coding</em>. Both are essential for writing nicer code.  At the beginning of the 
module we are going to focus on the
first, as this will cross over into all computing work people do.</p>

<!-- more -->

<p>The first five sessions will be </p>

<ol>
  <li>Introduction &amp; project set up (9 April)</li>
  <li>Version control with git (23 April) – this will be a longer
session, run with participants from the February software carpentry
bootcamp.</li>
  <li>Coding style (7 May)</li>
  <li>Abstraction and design (21 May)</li>
  <li>Testing code (4 June)</li>
</ol>

<p>Except for the version control session, we will meet from 2-3pm in E8C
212.</p>

<p>These sessions follow very much the same ideas as
<a href="http://www.software-carpentry.org">software carpentry</a>.  Where we
differ is that we will be focusing on <a href="http://r-project.org">R</a>, and
with less emphasis on command line tools and python.</p>

<p>The next sessions (18 June, 2 July, 16 July &amp; 30 July) will either
work on specific R skills or continue through issues arising from the
first five sessions, depending on demand.  Possible specific sessions
include</p>

<ul>
  <li>Data matching, models and avoiding duplication</li>
  <li>Higher order functions and functional programming</li>
  <li>The split/apply/combine pattern</li>
  <li>Creating better graphs (many possible sessions here)</li>
  <li>Code reuse and packaging</li>
  <li>Code profiling and optimisation</li>
  <li>Using and creating simple databases</li>
  <li>Text processing</li>
  <li>Numerical optimisation and algorithms</li>
  <li>Simulation models (an intro only!)</li>
  <li>Packages</li>
</ul>

<p>Along with the skills, we will be doing code review.  The idea will be
for a participant to meet with us immediately after one session and
discuss their problems with us.  They then work on their problem over
the next fortnight and in the next session we will discuss what the
issues were, the possibilities for overcoming them, and the eventual
solutions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
