<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: module | Nice R Code]]></title>
  <link href="http://nicercode.github.com/blog/categories/module/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://nicercode.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-03-11T06:26:26+11:00</updated>
  <id>http://nicercode.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Rich FitzJohn & Daniel Falster]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Plans for 'Nice R code module', Macquarie University 2013]]></title>
    <link href="http://nicercode.github.com/blog/2013-03-08-nice-r-code-2013-plans/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-08T09:58:00+11:00</updated>
    <id>http://nicercode.github.com/blog/nice-r-code-2013-plans</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to the Nice R code module. This module is targeted at researchers who
are already using R and want to write nicer code. By 'nicer' we mean code that
is easy to write, is easy to read, runs fast, gives reliable results, is easy
to reuse in new projects, and is easy to share with collaborators. When you
write nice code, you do better science, are more productive, and have more fun.</p>

<p>We have a tentative schedule of plans for the 2013 Nice R Code module. The
module consists of 9 one hour sessions and one 3 hour session.
The topics covered fall into two broad categories: <em>workflow</em> and
<em>coding</em>. Both are essential for writing nicer code.  At the beginning of the
module we are going to focus on the
first, as this will cross over into all computing work people do.</p>

<p>The first five sessions will be</p>

<ol>
<li>Introduction &amp; project set up (9 April)</li>
<li>Version control with git (23 April) -- this will be a longer
session, run with participants from the February software carpentry
bootcamp.</li>
<li>Coding style (7 May)</li>
<li>Testing code (21 May)</li>
<li>Abstraction and design (4 June)</li>
</ol>


<p>These sessions follow very much the same ideas as
<a href="http://www.software-carpentry.org">software carpentry</a>.  Where we
differ is that we will be focusing on <a href="http://r-project.org">R</a>, and
with less emphasis on command line tools and python.</p>

<p>The next sessions (18 June, 2 July, 16 July &amp; 30 July) will either
work on specific R skills or continue through issues arising from the
first five sessions, depending on demand.  Possible specific sessions
include</p>

<ul>
<li>Data matching, models and avoiding duplication</li>
<li>Higher order functions and functional programming</li>
<li>The split/apply/combine pattern</li>
<li>Creating better graphs (many possible sessions here)</li>
<li>Code reuse and packaging</li>
<li>Code profiling and optimisation</li>
<li>Using and creating simple databases</li>
</ul>


<p>Along with the skills, we will be doing code review.  The idea will be
for a participant to meet with us immediately after one session and
discuss their problems with us.  They then work on their problem over
the next fortnight and in the next session we will discuss what the
issues were, the possibilities for overcoming them, and the eventual
solutions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
